<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="ug.general-usage" version="8.0">
   <title>General Usage</title>
   <para> The general usage of PerfCake is covered in the following books and online resources. They
      provide useful hints, describe complex performance test scenarios and give guidance in solving
      real world problems.</para>
   <section>
      <title>PerfCake: Performance Testing Scenarios</title>
      <para>This a cookbook with recipes for creating complex performance testing scenarios to
         easily bootstrap your automated performance testing.</para>
      <para>The book is currently in the phase of preparation and we do not have much content yet.
         It is published on <xref xlink:href="https://leanpub.com/perfcake">LeanPub</xref> and we
         will keep releasing updates regularly. The book is for free with the option to donate a
         small amount of money to support our further work.</para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Performance Engineering</title>
      <para>This is another book that is currently a work in progress. It will teach you everything
         a succesful software engineer needs to know about performance testing from experts in the
         field.</para>
      <para>The book will be be published on <xref xlink:href="https://leanpub.com/perfengineering"
            >LeanPub</xref> and we will keep this documentation up-to-date with its current state.
         This time, the book won't be free but not very expensive either.</para>
      <para>In this book we examine many possible aspects of performance testing and figure out the
         best approaches to handle challenges along the way. We always analyze the problems, think
         about possible solutions and figure out the best within the given constraints.</para>
      <para>In the first part of the book, we go through the theory of performance testing and we
         define useful terms. Next, we will discuss what is important in performance testing, what
         to take care of, and how to best handle performance testing. Running real experiments is
         covered in the third part. In the last part we will discuss a design of an ideal
         performance testing tool and demonstrate it on a real implementation of an open-source
         performance testing framework PerfCake.</para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>YouTube Channels</title>
      <para> We are getting ready to create two YouTube channels with videos on performance testing.
         The first channel will cover performance testing in general, and the second channel will be
         more about creating real scenarios with PerfCake.</para>
   </section>
</chapter>
