<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="ug.perfcake-features.configuration.debug" version="8.0">
   <title>Debug Agent</title>
   <para>The Debug Agent is an experimental feature suited for performance scenario development. It
      has a significant performance drawback and must not be used for real testing.</para>
   <para>This agent publishes status of PerfCake components via JMX and can be read by utilities
      like <code>jvisualvm</code> (with MBean plugin).</para>
   <para>The agent can be started by configuring the system property <code>perfcake.debug</code> to
         <code>true</code> or by passing the <code>-d</code> or <code>--debug</code> command line
      options. For the agent to work properly, the JDK's <code>tools.jar</code> must be on the
      classpath. This necessity will be removed in Java 9. The PerfCake startup scripts try to
      configure the classpath accordingly but they still might fail. As a workaround, you might copy
      the <code>tools.jar</code> file to <code>${PERFCAKE_HOME}/lib/ext</code>.</para>
   <para>When there are multiple PerfCake instances running in the same JVM, they can be
      differentiated by setting <code>perfcake.debug.name</code> property (or <code>-dn</code>,
         <code>--debug-name</code> command line options). The default agent name is
         <code>perfcake-1</code>.</para>
   <para>The main purpose of the Debug Agent is for IDE plugin integration and debugging performance
      scenarios. The feature state will be claimed stable once there is enough testing with the IDE
      plugins and probably when we can remove the <code>tools.jar</code> dependency.</para>
   <figure xml:id="ug.perfcake-features.configuration.debug.jmx">
      <title>JMX tree with PerfCake debug information in <code>jvisualvm</code></title>
      <mediaobject>
         <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="./images/jmx.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" align="center"/>
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
   </figure>
</section>
